"The Best Mouthwash for
Halitosis (Bad Breath)"
Bad breath is an
underestimated problem affecting
a significant proportion
of the global population.
It seems most people
regularly report
encountering people
with halitosis.
Masking agents are frequently
used to cover up bad breath,
but studies have shown
that the use
of mouth rinses, sprays,
or mints containing
an agreeable masking odor
only have a short-term effect,
since you're not treating
the underlying cause,
so the exclusive usage
of masking products
can never be truly considered
an effective solution
to the problem.
The cause of bad breath
is oral putrefaction,
the degradation
of certain amino acids
mostly derived
by bacterial breakdown
of proteins in your mouth.
Specifically,
bacteria degrade
the sulfur-containing
amino acids,
such as cysteine
and methionine,
into stinky compounds
like the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide,
so-called
volatile sulfur compounds.
If you measure these compounds
spewing out of people's mouths
with machines
with names like Breathtron,
tooth brushing alone
does not significantly reduce
oral malodor.
Brushing alone reduces
sulfur breath compounds
from more than 450
down to about 300,
but that's still above the
stinky breath threshold of 250.
Add tongue cleaning
and you can drop that down
to right around the threshold,
but adding
an antiseptic mouthwash--
an antibacterial mouthwash--
did even better.
Okay, so what's
the best mouthwash to use?
To find out, researchers used
the cysteine challenge test.
Instead of giving people
dairy products,
which contain
the protein casein,
which is rich in the sulfur
amino acid cysteine,
they just had the participants
swish directly
with some cysteine
and then followed effectiveness
using odor-ograms.
For example, toothbrushing.
When people
swished with cysteine
before brushing their teeth,
here's the spike
in stinky sulfur compounds
spewing out of their mouths.
When they brushed their teeth
with water
and swished again at various
times over the rest of the day,
the spikes pretty much
looked the same,
meaning toothbrushing with water
didn't remove
many bad breath bacteria,
since the subjects were
spewing out similar spikes
starting just 20 minutes later.
Brushing with toothpaste
works better.
See how it knocks down the
next spike of stinky compounds
before the bacteria slowly
grow back throughout the day?
What about using
a tongue scraper?
Here's the odor-ogram.
Tongue scraping knocks it down
by about half
before coming back
over the next few hours.
What about chewing gum?
Here's that odor-ogram.
Some effect that disappears
over the subsequent few hours.
What about various mouthwashes?
First of all,
rinsing with water.
Useless.
Can be helpful
for morning breath,
to rinse any stagnation
that occurred overnight,
but during the day,
just rinsing with water
isn't clearing
many bad breath bacteria.
And swishing
with Scope mouthwash?
Just as useless as water.
Scope is
an anti-bacterial mouthwash
but it must not be good
at killing
the specific bacteria
that cause bad breath.
Peridex, though, cleaned house,
killing off those bacteria
even seven hours later.
What is Peridex?
That's just a brand name
for chlorhexidine.
Uh-oh: We know about that
from this video.
Chlorhexidine doesn't just get
rid of bad breath bacteria;
it also kills off
the good bacteria on your tongue
that help you make nitric oxide,
which protects your arteries,
and so chlorhexidine can raise
your blood pressure.
And that's not all.
Chlorhexidine
can stain your teeth.
That's not what you want
in a mouthwash.
Adverse effects are not rare.
Tooth staining, the buildup
of tartar, taste disturbance,
and damage to the lining of the
mouth have all been reported
with the use of chlorhexidine
in about 9 out of 10 people.
88 percent of people suffer
various side effects.
But hey, chlorhexidine
may be better
than mouthwashes
with hydrogen peroxide,
which may be carcinogenic,
potentially increasing
your risk of mouth cancer.
That's not just based
on studies on rodents, either.
Cultures of human
mouth lining cells
show significant DNA damage.
Triclosan was another
common antibacterial ingredient
in mouthwashes,
now effectively banned
in over-the-counter products.
Tongue scraping alone
doesn't always resolve
the problem of halitosis.
So, what can we use?
If bad breath persists
after improving tongue
and dental hygiene,
an active zinc-based mouth rinse
can be introduced.
Zinc binds directly to
the volatile sulfur compounds
and prevents them from
gassing out of your mouth.
Mouth rinses containing
ZnCl without alcohol
have been found to instantly
though temporarily
be effective for halitosis.
Researchers looked
at eight mouth rinses,
and the most effective
was a zinc chloride one
and the least effective
was Colgate Plax.
In fact, both of the alcohol
rinses were found to be
the least effective.
The thought is that they
may exacerbate halitosis
by drying up your mouth.
Here are some cysteine challenge
testing results
with different concentrations
of zinc chloride.
Note that all forms of zinc
don't work the same though.
Zinc chloride is very effective,
but zinc gluconate, which was
the difference between
regular Listerine
and an "advanced" Listerine,
didn't seem to work as well.